Guide to the New-York Historical Society Collection of Stereographs 1850-1964 (Bulk 1860-1900) PR 65
New-York Historical Society
- Subjects, 1860-1920
  - Subjects--Ships--Naval ships, [1860-1920] (Box 82)
    Identifier:PR-065-0858
    Warships: views of several kinds of warships, including sailing vessels, a ram, battleships, cruisers, dreadnoughts, a hospital ship, receiving ships and submarines; named vessels include: the D-3, E-1, K-1, K-6, Atlanta, Benham, Boston, Chicago, Delaware, Detroit, Dunderberg, Florida, Hampshire, Idaho, Iowa, Kansas, Maine, Kearsarge, Massachusetts, Michigan, Missouri, New Jersey, New York, North Carolina, North Dakota, Ohio, Olympia, Parker, Philadelphia, Pueblo, Raleigh, Santee, Seattle, Solace, Texas, Vermont, Vesuvius, Wisconsin, Wyoming, and British ships Cambridge and Terrible.
  - Subjects--Ships--Steamboats, [1870-1910] (Box 82)
    Identifier:PR-065-0859
    Steamboats: views of steamboats on rivers, in ship yards, a launching of a small steamboat, and steamboats moored at docks.
  - Subjects--Shops, [1870-1880] (Box 82)
    Identifier:PR-065-0860
    Shops: men standing in front of stores; interior views, including a general store, and women working making straw hats; interior of market building, including hogs for sale.
  - Subjects--Soda fountain, [1876] (Box 82)
    Identifier:PR-065-0861
    Soda water apparatus manufactured by James W. Tufts and used at the Centennial Exhibition.
  - Subjects--Spanish American War--Camp life, 1898 (Box 82)
    Identifier:PR-065-0862
    Spanish American War, Camp life: men arrayed in units, drilling, on parade, getting pay, by tents, getting supper, getting a shave, writing a letter, doing laundry, being tossed in a blanket, cavalry horses, including cavalry dashing through water; includes the Third N.Y. Volunteers, and Troop A. Volunteer Cavalry from New York City; troops training at Fort Slocum, including the 22nd New York State Guard.
  - Subjects--Spanish American War--Cuba, 1898-1899 (Box 82)
    Identifier:PR-065-0863
    Views in Cuba: fort at sugar mill, Caracas; Cienfuegos: a block house, a camp of Spanish soldiers shortly before leaving for Spain, American soldiers and officers; fort at El Caney, Guantanamo; Havana, including El Morro, the wreck of the Merrimack, wreck of the Vizcaya, Royal Palm Gardens, Gen. Blanco's palace, Canal Albears which supplies the city with water, Maj. Gen. Brooke and the Gov. General of Cuba; blockhouse in Manaznillo; cavalry of Gen. Gomez in Remedios; views in Santiago, including streets, camp life, San Juan Hill, men wounded during charge on San Juan Hill, artillery moving on Santiago; group of Afro-Cubans in the trenches waiting for the Spanish advance; group of men, including Afro-Cubans, in a Cuban prison; camp scenes, including men eating and man writing letter home.
    74 items
  - Subjects--Spanish American War--Dewey, 1898-1899 (Box 83)
    Identifier:PR-065-0864
    Admiral George Dewey: memorial style portraits, the admiral on the deck of the Olympia, Dewey and J.P. Morgan on the Olympia in New York, Dewey receiving a ceremonial sword, including views with McKinley, Secretary Long, and Cardinal Gibbon at the ceremony; Dewey's birthplace at Montpelier, Vt.
  - Subjects--Spanish American War--Embarkments, 1898 (Box 83)
    Identifier:PR-065-0865
    Embarkments: soldiers marching to boats, lounging on piers, kissing girls, having a meal, waiting by railroad cars, and Americans and Spanish leaving for home from Santiago; includes views of sailors and of Marines, as well as soldiers.
  - Subjects--Spanish American War--Marine, 1898-1899 (Box 83)
    Identifier:PR-065-0866
    Ships of the Spanish American War: battleships, cruisers, monitors, rams, and transports including the Brooklyn, Indiana, Iowa, Katahdin, Massachusetts, Minneapolis, Monterey, New York, Olympia, Oregon, Puritan, Roumania, St. Paul, San Francisco, Terror, Texas; the Monadnock in dry dock at Mare Island, California; Capt. Jewell of the Minneapolis being rowed ashore; wreckage of the Merrimac in Santiago Harbor, the Spanish Cruiser Reina Mercedes on its side, and the wreck of the Vicaya; officers and sailors on deck, including sailors at battle stations by large guns; Key West with the North American Squadron.
  - Subjects--Spanish American War--Marine, The Maine, 1898-1899 (Box 83)
    Identifier:PR-065-0867
    The Maine: views of the ship, the wreckage, including view of divers working in the wreck, hearses waiting for the dead, a line of hearses travelling through Havana, and the grave in Cuba, and coffins awaiting burial in their final resting place in Arlington National Cemetery; Captain, Sigsbee standing on deck.
  - Subjects--Spanish American War--Personalities, 1898-1902 (Box 84)
    Identifier:PR-065-0868
    Significant persons related to the Spanish American War: Capt. R. D. Evans (Fighting Bob), Lieut. Richmond Pearson Hobson, "The hero of the Merrimac," Maj. Gen. Fitzhugh Lee on horseback, President McKinley with Gen. Wheeler and others, Maj. Gen. Miles at front with staff, President Palma, first president of Cuba, Admiral William T. Sampson, Admiral W.S. Schley, General Shafter, General Young, Governor General Wood in crowd at docks, leaving Cuba, 1902, Col. Wykoff and officers of the 22nd U.S. Infantry.
  - Subjects--Spanish American War--Philippines, 1898-1899 (Box 84)
    Identifier:PR-065-0869
    Philippines in the Spanish American War: photograph of a painting of the battle of Manila; burnt deck of the Marie Teresa; American soldiers: wading the Norzararay River, 4th Infantry scouts with Philippine casualties, in trenches with Philippine dead after the battle of Malabon, in field shooting at Taquig, advancing on Malolos with a Hotchkiss Gun, entrenchment's at Zapote River and near Pasay; House of Congress on fire, Malolos; Santa Ana Church being used as a field hospital.
  - Subjects--Spanish American War--Posed scenes, 1898-1899 (Box 84)
    Identifier:PR-065-0870
    Posed domestic scenes relating to the Spanish American War: soldier's farewell, and his return to his wife after being wounded and believed dead at Santiago.
  - Subjects--Spanish American War--Rough Riders, 1898 (Box 84)
    Identifier:PR-065-0871
    Theodore Roosevelt and the Rough Riders: at Camp Wikoff, Montauk Point, N.Y., chaplain preaching to regiment, in camp in Tampa, and packing to leave, leaving from Tampa for Cuba, in Camp on San Juan Hill, with their mascot, a small wildcat, filling belts with cartridges, trenches on San Juan hill occupied by the Rough Riders, Capt. Curry, Col. Roosevelt on horseback, Roosevelt with Maj. Gen. Wheeler and other officers.
  - Subjects--Spanish American War--Groups, 1898-1899 (Box 84)
    Identifier:PR-065-0872
    People on the breastworks and sitting atop cannons viewing the battleships, Fortress Monroe, Virginia; wounded soldiers in a Key West Hospital.
  - Subjects--Sports, games, recreation, [1860-1910] (Box 84)
    Identifier:PR-065-0873
    Sports and games: a baseball team, beaches and swimming, including view of men at an indoor swimming pool, woman in bloomers on a safety bicycle, blind-man's-bluff, a boxing match between McGovern and Palmer, people boating on lakes and streams, including a view of a band in a boat, and a group of rowers with racing shells, people camping, people playing cards, croquet, women doing gymnastics out-of-doors, group with jump rope, minstrel group on a wagon, picnic groups, woman on a swing, women with tennis or other rackets, young women on teeter-totter, girls and women wading or sitting by streams, people watching a yacht race, man and woman playing unidentified game out of doors, groups relaxing on porches and in parks.
  - Subjects--Winter, [1860-1880] (Box 84)
    Identifier:PR-065-0874
    Winter scenes: a house in snow, park with trees broken under weight of ice, evergreens in the snow, icicles, an icy grotto with paper cut-outs of fairies.
  - Subjects--World War I, 1914-1918 (Box 85)
    Identifier:PR-065-0875
    World War I: drawings depicting battles; view of Serajevo, Canadian troops leaving Canada; Indian troops in France; British troops in France, French soldiers, Scots soldiers, parade of German troops in Berlin, military leaders from various nations, including Pershing, Beatty and others, battlefields, including trenches with soldiers and with German dead, desolate No-Man's Land, artillery, grave of Quentin Roosevelt, buried where he fell, Poincare and Joffre visiting the Somme front, dirigibles, including a wrecked Zeppelin, artillery, armored tanking moving through smoke, observation plane, bridge over the Marne, both standing and blown-up, one view with Red Cross train wreck, wounded soldiers at a hospital in Belgium, cathedral at Rheims bombed by the Germans, Wilson addressing Senate, submarines in dry dock, 3000 American soldiers ready for France, soldiers marching in Chicago, sailors training at Great Lakes, soldiers learning to use gas masks, American soldiers in London, men in life-jackets awaiting abandon ship drill, the US. Transport Leviathan, formerly the Vaterland, American soldiers back home, holding up babies, Clemenceau, Wilson and Lloyd George after signing of the treaty or Versailles, victory day celebrations in Paris, July 14, 1919, casket of the American Unknown soldier arriving on the Olympia at Washington, D.C.
- Comic and Sentimental, 1850-1910
  Comic and Sentimental Series: This series consists of views that were staged to tell a story or to depict a scene from literature. Items are arranged into groups, and each group has an Identifier, or unique number. The Identifier can be found within the group's Scope and Contents note. The groups are arranged by published series, or general topic.
  - Comic & Sentimental--Children, [1850-1910] (Box 85)
    Identifier:PR-065-0876
    Children in various staged situations: portraits, some with various props such as fishing poles and picture frames; children playing outdoors; babies, including bathing and sleeping; children and adults, including children at prayer, being bathed, sneaking food, being punished; children and animals: babies and children with cats and dogs, on horseback, with chickens; bedtime: children going to bed, in bed or asleep; boys and girls: girl and boy dining together, girl asking for a kiss; children playing dress-up, or dressed up to act out scenes or depict certain characters, including boy and "ghost," a scene in a country store, a widow, pretending to be a chemist, pretending to be grandparents, Tom Whittington; children and dolls, including pretend baptism scene, doll carriages, tea parties, and African American dolls, Noah, the ark and animals; children reading or in school, including playing practical jokes, and standing on chairs to avoid rats or mice.
  - Comic & Sentimental--Dance, 1897-1905 (Box 86)
    Identifier:PR-065-0877
    Dancing: girls in dancing school; woman read for the ball, people dancing, and woman exhausted after the ball, drawing of servants dancing while family is out of town, group dancing under a tree.
  - Comic & Sentimental--Diables, [1868-1880] (Box 86)
    Identifier:PR-065-0878
    Diables, or Journey in Hell, a French series using table-top photography and dolls depicting devils and skeletons in various situations including the entrance to hell, skeletons in a cauldron, in carriages, omnibuses and on bicycles, a devils Sabbath, a boat regatta, and the Resurrection.
  - Comic & Sentimental--Domestic activities, [1860-1897] (Box 86)
    Identifier:PR-065-0879
    Domestic scenes: misunderstandings with maids, people dining, bathing, dressing, reading, playing games, sewing, playing piano, couples going to bed, man sleepwalking, removing a bandage, women playing trick on sleeping man, man chasing a rat under a bed, people fleeing a fire and a second slide with people heading the other way captioned "Who hollowed fire?"
  - Comic & Sentimental--Ethnic stereotypes, [1865-1890] (Box 86)
    Identifier:PR-065-0880
    Ethnic stereotypes: men playing cards, including man in costume to appear Chinese; African Americans or European Americans in blackface depicting stereotypical situations, including the character of Sambo.
  - Comic & Sentimental--Evils of drink, 1870, 1892 (Box 86)
    Identifier:PR-065-0881
    Evils of drink: a temperance series of 12 views depicting the downward progress of man who takes to drink; disheveled man having a "nightcap" in his bedroom.
  - Comic & Sentimental--Holidays, [1860-1880] (Box 86)
    Identifier:PR-065-0882
    Holidays: people attending a wake; family gathered for thanksgiving in New Hampshire; Christmas: Santa Claus looking up those who are good in a large book child waiting for Santa Claus, Santa visiting while child is asleep, Santa "bewildered by the clamoring of Christmas Belles," woman standing under mistletoe, ignored by roomful of men; group gathered for New Year's Ball, girl with New Year's greeting.
  - Comic & Sentimental--Male/Female Role reversal, 1876-1902 (Box 86)
    Identifier:PR-065-0883
    Role reversal, including images depicting "the New Woman," often depicted in bloomer with bicycle; includes men serving in female roles such as cooking, doing laundry and child care; woman courting a man.
  - Comic & Sentimental--Marriage, [1870-1907] (Box 86)
    Identifier:PR-065-0884
    Marriage: man proposing, women dressing for wedding, wedding ceremonies and dinners, newlyweds alone, newlyweds decorating their home.
  - Comic & Sentimental--Marital infidelity, [1899-1905] (Box 86)
    Identifier:PR-065-0885
    Marital infidelity: man caught with maid, man caught entertaining another woman at home, man lamenting leaving his wife for another woman, wife hiding lover under the table, man flirting with woman at the office.
  - Comic & Sentimental--Music and entertainments, [1870] (Box 86)
    Identifier:PR-065-0886
    Music and entertainment: Carol singers; a choir singing and in a dispute, group arriving and surprising couple with a party, couple in a museum, wife pulling husband away from a classical-style sculpture of a woman.
  - Comic & Sentimental--Occupations, [1865- 1904] (Box 86)
    Identifier:PR-065-0887
    Occupations: woman selling oysters, a gravedigger, peddler in the stocks for not having a license, barbers working on customers, dentists, and shoe salesmen fitting women and being told "Don't get above your business"; post mistress in a village post office.
  - Comic & Sentimental--Outdoor activities, [1870-1900] (Box 87)
    Identifier:PR-065-0888
    Outdoor activities: women swimming and relaxing near the water, including scene with perturbed man in a rowboat; skinny-dipping man trapped by women coming upon him; men and women fishing and romancing; girls feeding the ducks, man carrying woman through snowy scene; man feeding large dog at train station; woman harnessing buggy horse; man peering over fence and eavesdropping.
  - Comic & Sentimental--Risque, [1890-1900] (Box 87)
    Identifier:PR-065-0889
    Risqué views: bathing beauties; woman with flowers; woman asleep; painting of nude woman surrounded with flowers.
  - Comic & Sentimental--Romance, [1860-1900] (Box 87)
    Identifier:PR-065-0890
    Romance: young man and woman, entitled "her first beau"; couples kissing: under haystack, in parlors and kitchens, over a wall, in a buggy, and man with bicycle kissing the hand of a woman while another sneaks up with a broom; man wooing milk maid; couples caught fallen asleep in one another's arms and pulled apart by the ears; father frightening his daughter's suitor in his masquerade costume; woman challenging man to catch a butterfly; woman asleep dreaming of love.
  - Comic & Sentimental--Women, [1860-1900] (Box 87)
    Identifier:PR-065-0891
    Women: women socializing, drinking tea, gossiping, dressing to go out, playing at fencing.
  - Comic & Sentimental--European, Alphabets des costumes, [1860] (Box 87)
    Identifier:PR-065-0892
    The letters A and Y from a series called Alphabet des costumes, the A depicting "Auvergnats," a farm family in their home, and the Y a group of Yankee men brawling in a tavern.
  - Comic & Sentimental--European, angels, dreams, ghosts, [1850-1865] (Box 87)
    Identifier:PR-065-0893
    Angels, dreams and ghosts: man being confronted by a spirit; country man surprised by a ghost; woman dreaming of spirit called Mustard after seeing "Pepper's ghost"; "The ascension of Marguerite, angels bearing woman aloft; angels bending over bed of praying woman; angel looking over family bereft by grave of loved one; many of the views are made by using a double exposure.
  - Comic & Sentimental--European, Characters & scenes, [1850-1865] (Box 87)
    Identifier:PR-065-0894
    Characters and scenes: winter, showing a well to do couple and a poor woman; "Life's phases, showing well to do woman and ragged woman; [Irish] man reading sign advertising transportation to N.Y. on the Shamrock; woman dressed in costume of time of Charles II, holding hawk; two views depicting "exchange is no robbery": man exchanging his clothes for better, and women exchanging a rat for a rabbit; two views of a miser, one happy alone with his money, another fearful when someone intrudes; child flying through the air in a sieve to illustrate a text from Macbeth; two views illustrating "The old curiosity shop"; "Robinson Crusoe"; Little Red riding Hood; man trying to board an omnibus; couple in stocks; two scenes, possibly from the Crimea War time, one showing woman distraught after receiving a letter form the war, another a Highland soldier returning home to his cottage and his wife.
  - Comic & Sentimental--European, Children, [1850-1870] (Box 87)
    Identifier:PR-065-0895
    Children: parents and infants, including both mothers and fathers holding and feeding babies; portraits of children; children in school and having lessons; children with adults, including mothers and grandmothers; children playing, including a boy on a rocking horse, children playing dress-up, or dressed up as characters, playing marbles; boy with hurdy-gurdy thumbing his nose; boys being punished; boys fighting.
  - Comic & Sentimental--European, Crinolines, [1850] (Box 87)
    Identifier:PR-065-0896
    Views poking fun at the fashion of crinolines: children playing dress up with barrel staves used for crinolines; immense crinolines, some interfering with social situations; crinolines and omnibuses; women asking a blessing on their crinolines.
  - Comic & Sentimental--European, Domestic scenes, [1850-1860] (Box 87)
    Identifier:PR-065-0897
    Domestic scenes: people sleeping, bathing, sleepwalking, couples: discussing politics, playing music, arguing, and in bed; man walking in on woman bathing; man looking for towel when he has soap in his eyes; man receiving the news of the birth of his son; man presented with twins; soldier returning home to find child that can't be his; view titled "Sold up" possibly depicting an auction of household items.
  - Comic & Sentimental--European, Entertainment, [1850-1865] (Box 88)
    Identifier:PR-065-0898
    Entertainments, games, recreation: couple playing chess, groups playing blind-man's bluff; le jeu de la Main-Chaude; playing cards; playing music; calling on friends and entertaining at home, including dinner parties and salons, a masquerade, dancing, dining in a restaurant, attending theatre, people caroling, group of acrobats at Greenwich Fair, theatrical scenes, including woman on horseback and a print depicting a scene in William Tell; group of women at Court of St. James, a seaside excursion, groups on Derby day, including views of people in carts, wagons and omnibuses, betting and along the rail during the race, group picnicking, man hunting; woman.
  - Comic & Sentimental--European, Holidays, [1850-1860] (Box 88)
    Identifier:PR-065-0899
    Holidays: people playing April Fool's jokes; a queen of the May; boys and Guy Fawkes effigy.
  - Comic & Sentimental--European, Occupations, [1850-1870] (Box 88)
    Identifier:PR-065-0900
    Occupations: a lace maker; woman selling ducks and other fowl; barbers; fishwoman trying to sell a sole to a courting couple; a market scene.
  - Comic & Sentimental--European, Religion, [1850-1865] (Box 88)
    Identifier:PR-065-0901
    Religion: four views of dioramas the Stations of the Cross; a funeral; baptisms; people entering, attending and leaving church, including a girl being turned out of church; group at confirmation; group receiving first communion; woman making confession; reception and profession of a Sister of Mercy; priest eating on a fast day; monks playing cards; monk sneaking a woman into a monastery.
  - Comic & Sentimental--European, Risque, [1850-1870] (Box 88)
    Identifier:PR-065-0902
    Women in risqué situations including dressing, washing their feet, showing their legs on a swing, bending over a book; a ballerina standing on stage; two women punishing boy who was peaking at them; man walking in on woman in a hotel room; tradesmen looking at legs of maid who is washing step.
  - Comic & Sentimental--European, Romance and marriage, [1850-1870] (Box 88)
    Identifier:PR-065-0903
    Romance and marriage: courtship in parlors, in shops, out of doors, in humble kitchens, through windows, serenading; reluctant love, bashful love; man dressing to go courting; woman looking out her door for her beau; "one too many"; May - December romance; women hiding lovers, including maid hiding lover and being romanced by the master, with the lover then beating-up the master; women being romanced by salesman; "the attentive maid"; woman eloping; man measuring woman's finger for wedding ring; dressing the bride; wedding parties with the priest; wedding party leaving the church; couple in their new home; monk looking at women; maid listening to shepherd playing flute.
  - Comic & Sentimental--European, Still-lifes, [1850] (Box 88)
    Identifier:PR-065-0904
    Still-lifes: table with food; vase of flowers; [both images damaged].
  - Comic & Sentimental--European, Women, [1850-1870] (Box 88)
    Identifier:PR-065-0905
    Women: portraits; writing and sealing letters; maid reading letter over her mistresses shoulder; women sleeping, dressing and having their hair dressed, eating strawberries, having fortune read, breaking a wishbone; woman reading to another who is bed sick.